[Music]
foreign
Professor Dave and Chegg here we should
recall from General chemistry the
concept of an equilibrium this is a
system that has a forward reaction and a
reverse reaction where the products of
one act as the reactants for the other
let's review some important Concepts
pertaining to equilibria and how they
will be important in organic chemistry
here is a generalized equilibrium and
the equilibrium constant expression that
will go along with it remember these
involve an equilibrium constant K being
equal to the concentrations of the
products each raised to the power of
their stoichiometric coefficients over
the concentrations of the reactants each
raised to the power of their
stoichiometric coefficients
K tells us where the equilibrium lies if
it's much greater than one it's because
the numerator of this expression is very
large which means products are strongly
favored if it's a tiny fraction of one
it's because the denominator of this
expression is very large which means
reactants are strongly favored the
direction that will be favored is
determined by Delta G or the change in
Gibbs free energy if the forward
reaction results in products that are
much lower in energy than the reactants
Delta G for this process will be
negative making it spontaneous and this
will be the favored Direction recall
that a process with a negative Delta G
is called exergonic and if positive it's
called endergonic if we want to talk
about the standard free energy change we
have this symbol in superscript and this
will denote standard conditions meaning
room temperature and one atmosphere of
pressure we can relate the standard free
energy change to the equilibrium
constant using one of the two following
equations where R is this version of the
gas constant we should also remember
this other important equation which
shows how the change in free energy
depends on the change in enthalpy and
the change in entropy as well as the
temperature the change in enthalpy is
the heat exchanged at constant pressure
so essentially the difference in bond
enthalpies if a reaction is exothermic
Delta H is negative and heat is released
if endothermic Delta H is positive and
heat must be absorbed the change in
entropy is the change in the dispersal
of matter and energy so if a molecule
decomposes into two smaller molecules
this is entropically favorable which
means a positive Delta s if two
fragments fuse to form a larger molecule
this is entropically unfavorable which
means a negative Delta s for the system
different combinations of enthalpic and
entropic favorability can result in
either exergonic or endergonic reactions
which may also depend on the temperature
of the system
these were all Concepts that should be
familiar from General chemistry but they
are worth reviewing as this terminology
and the associated equations will come
up over and over again as we examine
organic reactions Professor Dave for
Chegg see you next time